Dreyer family. Papers of the Dreyer family, 1778-1928: A Finding Aid
Papers of the Dreyer family 1778-1928
MC 581
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Dreyer family
6.05 linear ft. (14 + 1/2 file boxes)
Correspondence and other papers of members of the Dreier family, mostly merchants and pastors in northern Germany and businessmen in the United States and their wives.
Accession number: 86-M9
The papers of the Dreier family were given to the Schlesinger Library by John C. Dreier in 1986.
Access Restrictions:
Access. Unrestricted.
BIOGRAPHY
When Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) married Dorothea Adelheid Uhthoff (b.1774) in 1797 the Dreiers were a relatively wealthy merchant family from Bremen in northern Germany. The couple had four sons and a daughter who died at the age of eleven.
The eldest son Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), married to Thaddea Henriette Schacht (b.1806), was also a merchant in Bremen but got into financial troubles during the the 1850s. The second son, Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805), worked as a pastor in Mittelsbueren and Grambke (today part of the state Bremen), and married first Metta Lucie Wilhelmine Noltenius (b.1800) who died five years after the marriage and then Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Lampe (b.1813). The third son, August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808), who became a merchant in Bremen also married twice: Sophie Friederike Elisabeth (Betty) Focke (b.1808) in 1837 and 32 years later Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Meinertzhagen (b.1814). The youngest son, Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811), became a pastor but had some problems in securing an appropriate rectorate. After working in Lehe, at the House of Emigrants (Auswandererhaus) in Bremerhaven and Blumenthal he finally succeded in getting a post in Neuenkirchen near Farge (today part of the state Bremen), where he lived until his death with his wife Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Hotzen (b.1817).
Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) and his wife Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) had seven children. Three daughters died as children as did a son at the age of 19. Their eldest child, Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828), became a merchant and emigrated to the United States at the end of the 1840s. There he worked for the steel distributor Naylor Co. in New York, where he became a quite wealthy businessman. In 1864 he married his cousin, Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (b.1840), the daughter of his uncle Heinrich Eduard Dreier and his wife Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Dreier, and took her with him to the United States where the couple lived mainly in Brooklyn. His sister, Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829), never married and stayed with her father in Bremen. After being ill and partly bedridden for several years she died at the age of 41. Her brother, Karl Wilhelm Dreier (b.1836), was sent to the boarding school Rauhes Haus in Hamburg. After several years as seaman (finally as officer on a steamship) he became a farmer in Iowa. He married Bertha Obermann (b.1846) in 1869, and after her death eight years later, Marie Adelheid Kant (b.1857). The brother of Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803),; Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805), and his two wives had ten children, his brother August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808) and his first wife, four. The youngest of the four brothers, Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811) and his wife Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Dreier (b.1817) had three children. The eldest daughter Margaretha (Meta) Dreier (b.1839) married pharmacist Friedrich Heinrich Wilhelm Knoch (b.1826), who had pharmacies in Blumenthal, Bad Pyrmont, Giessen and Krefeld. The second child, Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (b.1840), married, as already mentioned, her cousin and moved to the United States. Her brother, Johann Caspar Ludwig Dreier (b.1843), never married. He followed his sister and his cousin to the United States during the 1860s where he worked for Naylor Co. and an insurance company. His attempt to establish his own enterprise failed after a short time. He later returned to Germany.
Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828) and his wife (and cousin) Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (b.1840) had seven children. Their daughters, Marie (Mary) Elisabeth Dreier (b.1875) and Katherine Sophie Dreier (b.1877), became quite well known, the first as a social reformer (her papers can also be found at the Schlesinger Library, MC 309), the second as an artist and a patron of the arts.
ARRANGEMENT
The collection is arranged in six series:
Series I. First generation: correspondence, 1802-1816, n.d. (#1.1-1.2)
Series II. Second generation: correspondence, 1784-1862, n.d. (#1.3-1.14, 2.3, 3.5)
Series III. Third generation: correspondence, 1817-1881, n.d. (#1.15-6.7)
Subseries A. Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) and Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806), 1817-1873, n.d., (#1.15-1.30, 2.1-2.2, 2.4-2.5, 5.6-5.17)
Subseries B. Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) and his second wife Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813), 1817-1875, n.d., (#2.6.-2.9, 6.1-6.3)
Subseries C. August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808), 1830-1879, (#2.10-2.13)
Subseries D. Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811), and Margaretha (Meta) Thibeta Dreier (née Hotzen, b.1817), 1829-1881, n.d., (#2.14-3.4, 3.6-5.5, 6.4-6.7)
Series IV. Fourth generation: correspondence, 1837-1893, n.d. (#6.8-14.3)
Subseries A. Children of Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) and Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) and their spouses, 1837-1881, n.d., (#6.8-11.11, 13.9)
Subseries B. Children of Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) and his first wife Metta Lucie Wilhelmine Dreier (née Noltenius, b.1800) and his second wife Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813), 1860-1869, (#11.12-11.15)
Subseries C. Children of August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808) and his first wife Sophie Friederike Elisabeth (Betty) Dreier (née Focke, b.1808), 1863-1870, n.d., (#11.16-11.17, 12.21)
Subseries D. Children of Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811), and Margaretha (Meta) Thibeta Dreier (née Hotzen, b.1817) and their spouses, 1848-1893, n.d., (#11.18-12.20, 12.22-13.8, 13.10-14.3)
Series V. Fifth generation: correspondence, 1872-1917, n.d. (#14.4.-14.17)
Series VI. Unidentifiable letters and other papers, 1778-1928, n.d. (#14.18-15.4)
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection includes correspondence between single members of the Dreier family and correspondence with related families and other persons. Furthermore it contains additional materials such as the private papers of single family members and handwritten poems -- most written on the occasion of family celebrations. The collection offers an excellent insight into the life of a relatively wealthy north German family of merchants and pastors: its economic conditions and social life, the relationship among spouses, siblings, parents and their children, the intellectual background of single family members, the handling of diseases and cases of death (foremost of children), education, schooling and, not least, into contemporary politics. Due to the fact that one couple (two cousins) and two further family members went to the United States (with quite different economic success) in the middle of the 19th century, the collection is also an excellent source for the history of emigration from Germany to America. Particularly interesting for the history of women in the 19th century is the correspondence of women of the third and fourth generation with their mothers or daughters, where, for example, pregnancy, birth, or the loss of children and their education play an important role. The correspondence is in the German cursive writing of the 19th century and is extremely difficult to read without training.
Series I, FIRST GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1802-1816, n.d. (#1.1-1.2), contains letters of Mr. and Mrs. Helmerich Uhthoff, parents of Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to their daughter and to grandson Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803).
Series II, SECOND GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1784-1862, n.d. (#1.3-1.14, 2.3, 3.5), contains letters from or to Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), as well as correspondence of single members of the Uhthoff and the Hotzen family and of Pastor Mueller who had quite a close relationship to several family members.
Series III, THIRD GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1817-1881, n.d. (#1.15-6.7), contains correspondence of the four sons of Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) and their spouses.
Subseries A, Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) and Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806),1817-1873, n.d. (#1.15-2.2, 2.4-2.5, 5.6-5.17), contains correspondence with the two spouses.
Subseries B, Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) and his second wife Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813),1817-1875, n.d., (#2.6-2.9, 6.1-6.3), contains correspondence with the two spouses.
Subseries C, August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808),1830-1879, (#2.10-2.13), contains his letters to other family members. Letters from his two wives are not found in this collection.
Subseries D, Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811) and Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Dreier (née Hotzen, b.1817),1829-1881, n.d., (#2.14-3.4, 3.6-5.5, 6.4-6.7), contains correspondence with the two spouses.
Series IV, FOURTH GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1837-1893, n.d., (#6.8-14.3), contains correspondence of the children of the four sons of Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) and their spouses.
Subseries A, Children of Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) and Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) and their spouses, 1837-1881, n.d., (#6.8-11.11, 13.9), contains correspondence of Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828),; Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829),; Karl Wilhelm Dreier (b.1836), his first wife Bertha Dreier (née Obermann, b.1846) and Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1838). The correspondence of the wife (and at the same time cousin) of Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828) can be found in Subseries D.
Subseries B, Children of Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) and his first wife Metta Lucie Wilhelmine Dreier (née Noltenius, b.1800) and his second wife Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813),1860-1869, (#11.12-11.15), contains a few letters of Johannes Caspar Heinrich Dreier (b.1833),; Cornelius Heinrich Dreier (b.1838),; Dorothea (Doris) Hermanna Dreier (b.1841) and Magdalene Henriette Wilhelmine Dreier (b.1842).
Subseries C, Children of August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808) and his first wife Sophie Friederike Elisabeth (Betty) Dreier (née Focke, b.1808),1863-1870, n.d., (#11.16-11.17, 12.21), contains a few letters of Christine Emma Elisabeth Pferdmenges (née Dreier, b.1842) (?) and Johannes Theodor Ernst Dreier (b.1844).
Subseries D, Children of Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811) and Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Dreier (née Hotzen, b.1817) and their spouses, 1848-1893, n.d., (#11.18-12.20, 12.22-13.8, 13.10-14.3), contains correspondence of Margaretha (Meta) Knoch (neé Dreier, b.1839), her husband Friedrich Heinrich Wilhelm Knoch (b.1826),; Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Dreier, b.1840),; Johann Caspar Ludwig Dreier (b.1843) and Carl Radatz, a former foster child of the couple. The correspondence of the husband (and at the same time cousin) of Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Dreier, b.1840) can be found in Subseries A.
Series V, FIFTH GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1872-1917, n.d., (#14.4-14.17), contains correspondence of the grandchildren of the four sons of Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774)
Series VI, UNIDENTIFIABLE LETTERS AND OTHER PAPERS, 1778-1928, n.d., (#14.18-15.4), contains unidentifiable letters and private papers of different members of the Dreier family, mostly bills, notebooks and handwritten poems (mostly religious or on the occasion of family celebrations).
INVENTORY
- Series I. FIRST GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1802-1816, n.d. (#1.1-1.2)
  Series I, FIRST GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1802-1816, n.d. (#1.1-1.2), contains letters of Mr. and Mrs. Helmerich Uhthoff, parents of Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to their daughter and to grandson Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803).
  - Mrs. Helmerich Uhthoff to her daughter Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), 1802, n.d.; mainly re: birthday wishes, 1.1.
  - Helmerich Uhthoff to his grandson Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1803 and 1816; re: wishes at occasion of Gustav Theodor's baptism, 1.2.
- Series II. SECOND GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1784-1862, n.d. (#1.3-1.14, 2.3, 3.5)
  Series II, SECOND GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1784-1862, n.d. (#1.3-1.14, 2.3, 3.5), contains letters from or to Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), as well as correspondence of single members of the Uhthoff and the Hotzen family and of Pastor Mueller who had quite a close relationship to several family members.
  - Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to her son Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1819-1843, n.d.; also includes one letter with a note from his brother August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808), 1.4.
  - Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to her grandson Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828), 1837, n.d., 1.5.
  - Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to her daughter-in-law Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806), 1840, n.d., 1.6.
  - Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to Pastor Mueller, 1830-1831, n.d.; re: rectorate for her son Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805), 1.7.
  - Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) to Mrs. Klenken, 1829-1838, n.d., 1.8.
  - To Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) from different persons, 1813-1829; re: religious topics; sermons and religious writings; books (e.g. Heinrich Stillings Lehr-Jahre); school enrollment of her daughter Anna Dorothea (Doris) Dreier (b.1806); life-threatening disease of friend's newborn baby; disease, cure and treatment of friend's son; instruction at home; alms, 1.9.
  - To Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) from different persons, 1830, n.d.; re: religious topics, 1.10.
  - Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) to his wife Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), 1800-1821, n.d.; re: election of preacher; birthday wishes, 1.11.
  - Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) to Mr. Roesgen, 1784; re: business dealings, 1.12.
  - To Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) from Johann Arnold Roesgen, 1784-1788, mainly re: commerce and business dealings, 1.3.
  - Leo Uhthoff to his sister Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), 1830; re: business dealings, 1.13.
  - Leo Uhthoff to his nephew Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1825-1835, re: Gustav Theodor Dreier's engagement; business dealings and financial transactions, 2.3.
  - To Mrs. Hotzen, mother-in-law of Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811), from different persons, 1839, 1862, 3.5.
  - Pastor Mueller to different members of Dreier family, foremost to Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) and to Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1824-1835; re: job as housekeeper for Mueller's sister Lene; Mueller's state of health; cure and medical treatment; choice of doctors; religious topics; Dorothea Adelheid Dreier's sons; greetings at occasion of family celebrations; asset of welfare fund; matters of inheritance, 1.14.
- Series III. THIRD GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1817-1881, n.d. (#1.15-6.7)
  Series III, THIRD GENERATION: CORRESPONDENCE, 1817-1881, n.d. (#1.15-6.7), contains correspondence of the four sons of Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774) and their spouses.
  - Subseries A. Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) and Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) 1817-1873, n.d. (#1.15-2.2, 2.4-2.5, 5.6-5.17)
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his father Johann Caspar Dreier (formerly Dreyer, b.1758), 1817, 1.15.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his mother Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), 1843, 1.16.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his wife Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806), 1827-1857, n.d.; re: greetings on their wedding day 1827; business travels to Netherlands and to other German states; education; their children and children of friends; pastors; Christian conduct of life, 1.17.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to all his children, 1840, 1.18.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his son Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828), 1839-1871, n.d.; re: vacation at North Sea and in Northern Germany; disease of his brother Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805); reflections on his visit at his son's home in United States, 1.19.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his daughter Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829), 1864, 1.20.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his son Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828) and daughter-in-law Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Dreier, b.1840), 1865; re: marrige of Gustav Theodor's nephew Johannes Caspar Heinrich Dreier (b.1833) with Johanne Marie Dreier (née Wuelbern, b.1845); family affairs; economic consequences of civil war; cruise from New York to Bremerhaven, 1.21.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his daughter-in-law Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Dreier, b.1840), 1864-1872; re: birthday wishes; travels to Karlsbad; family affairs; disease and death of his bedridden daughter Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829); pastors and sermons; birthday menu; birth and death of grandchildren, cultural events; Franco-Prussian War (1870-1871), 1.22.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his sister-in-law Margaretha (Meta) Thibetha Dreier (née Hotzen, b.1817), 1865 and 1868; re: agony of his sister-in-law Sophie Friederike Elisabeth (Betty) Dreier (née Focke, b.1808), 1.23.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to his granddaughter Margaretha (Gretchen) Dreier Robins (née Dreier, b.1868), 1872, 1.24.
    - Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) to Pastor Mueller, 1830-1832, n.d., 1.25.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from his cousin H. Uhthoff, 1851, 1.26.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from D. (?) Kaufmann, 1847-1849; re: matters of inheritance, 1.27.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from his cousin (?) Eduard in New York, 1833-1838, n.d.; re: business dealings, 1.28.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from different relatives, 1830-1873; re: fireworks at Heidelberg Castle (Schlossbeleuchtung) and festivities in honor of Grand Duke of Baden and his wife; death of Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829), 1.29.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from Pastor Kohlmann, 1836-1860, re: building of churches; letters of condolence on occasion of death of Gustav Theodor Dreier's son Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1838) and of his wife Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b. 1806), 1.30.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from Dr. Johann Hinrich Wichern, 1852-1854, n.d.; re: education of Karl Wilhelm Dreier (b.1836) at boarding school "Rauhes Haus" in Hamburg-Horn; curricula; report card; bill, 2.4.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from Joh. F. Philippi, 1826-1833; re: business; political situation in Vera Cruz, 2.5.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from different persons, 1825-1871; re: greetings at occasion of family celebrations; gratitude for a charitable donation to pastor of Mengershausen; collection for Protestant parish; inquiries into company in Boston; narration of John Obermann, father of Gustav Theodor Dreier's daughter-in-law Bertha Dreier (née Obermann, b.1846), of wedding of Bertha and Karl Wilhem Dreier (b.1836) and on life and farming in New London, Iowa; Obermann's comments on Franco-Prussian War (1870-1871) and future of Germany; business dealings; description of former female employee of Dreiers: life in Indiana, Morgan's Raid during Civil War, crop failure, delinquency, behavior of former slaves after liberation, 2.1.
    - To Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803) from different persons, n.d.; re: application as clerk due to problems in business, 2.2.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her mother-in-law Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), 1828-1845, n.d., 5.6.
    - "Brautbrief" (antenuptial contract) between Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) and Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1827, 5.7.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her husband Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1826-1833: love letters during their time of engagement, 5.8.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her husband Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1834-1838; re: situation at home while husband is away on business; cure at North Sea, 5.9.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her husband Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1839-1848; re: situation at home while husband is away on business, 5.10.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her husband Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1850-1859; re: situation at home while husband is away on business; cure in Bad Lippspringe and bill for food and accommodation in health resort, 5.11.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her husband Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), n.d., 5.12.
    - Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) to her son Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828), 1839, 1844; re: cure at North Sea, 5.13.
    - To Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) from different persons, 1819-1829; re: life of friend as governess and teacher in householt of a forester family, 5.14.
    - To Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) from different persons, 1830-1832; re: reflections of friend on her admirer, love, motherhood and job as governess and teacher, 5.15.
    - To Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) from different persons, 1833-1858, 5.16.
    - To Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806) from different persons, n.d., 5.17.
  - Subseries B. Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) and his second wife Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813), 1817-1875, n.d. (#2.6-2.9, 6.1-6.3)
    - Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) to his mother Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Uhthoff, b.1774), 1845; re: vacation in Harz Mountains, 2.6.
    - Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) to his brother Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), one letter also addressed to his brother Heinrich Eduard Dreier (b.1811), 1817-1871, n.d.; re: birthday wishes; studies in Berlin; vacation; finances; matters of inheritance; death of Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829); Franco-Prussian War (1870-1871), 2.7.
    - Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) to his nephew Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828) and Dorothea Adelheid Dreier (née Dreier, b.1840), 1861-1875; re: family affairs; earthquake in Peru (1868), 2.8.
    - Julius Alexander Dreier (b.1805) to Pastor Mueller, 1830-1832, n.d.; re: professional topics as pastors, 2.9.
    - Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813) to her sister-in-law Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b.1806), 1853, 1857, n.d., 6.1.
    - Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813) to her brother-in-law Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1870, 6.2.
    - Margaretha (Meta) Catharina Dreier (née Lampe, b.1813) to her niece Dorothea Henriette Christine Dreier (b.1829), 1865, 6.3.
  - Subseries C. August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808), 1830-1879 (#2.10-2.13)
    - August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808) to his brother Gustav Theodor Dreier (b.1803), 1832-1833; re: period of business training in United States, 2.10.
    - August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808) to his sister-in-law Thaddea Henriette Dreier (née Schacht, b. 1806), 1832, 2.11.
    - August Ferdinand Dreier (b.1808) to his nephew Johann Caspar Theodor Dreier (b.1828), 1879; re: birthday wishes, 2.12.